<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<root>
	<English>
		<Parameters>
			<Title>&lt;B&gt;Electrostatics&lt;/B&gt;</Title>
			<Number>1</Number>
			<Play>Play</Play>
			<Pause>Pause</Pause>
			<Previous>Previous</Previous>
			<Next>Next</Next>
			<Replay>Replay</Replay>
			<Restart>Restart</Restart>
			<Section>Section </Section>
			<End>&lt;B&gt;You have completed this Chapter.&lt;B/&gt;</End>
			<End1>Use the drop down menu above to replay a particular section.</End1>
			<Copyright>Copyright 2010 - All rights reserved</Copyright>

			<CopyrightEnd>Content and animation by EduLab</CopyrightEnd>
			<Sens>Sens de propagation</Sens>
			<Chap>&lt;B&gt;Chap&lt;B/&gt;</Chap>
		</Parameters>
		<Section>
   			<0>I. Introduction</0>
			<1>If we rub a plastic pen with a piece of cloth then we bring it close to a bit of paper, we will notice that the pen attracts the paper at the rubbed place.</1>
			<2>This Phenomenon and others was reported by Thales de Milet, around 600 B.C. He had observed the attraction of light straw by rubbed yellow amber. The word "electricity" is derived from "elektron" which means amber in Greek.</2>
			<3>In order to explain this phenomenon, in addition to other natural phenomena, scientists have attributed to matter a property of electrification. Electric forces can be explained by introducing the concept of electric charges.</3>
		</Section>		
		<Section>
   			<0>II. Electrostatic interaction</0>
			<1>Experimentally, we can observe the existence of two kinds of electricity, thus the concept of positive and negative charges is introduced.</1>
			<2>- two bodies of like charges repel each other.</2>
			<3>- two bodies of unlike charges attract each another.</3>
			<4>In the International System of Units, the unit of electric charges is the Coulomb (C).</4>
		</Section>
		<Section>
   			<0>III. The electric aspect of matter</0>
			<1>Scientists have proposed a model to describe the structure of the matter. According to this model:</1>
			<2>- All kinds of matter are composed of atoms, with different shapes and dimensions.</2>
			<3>- Every atom is composed of a nucleus, around which there are negatively charged electrons in continuous motion.</3>
			<4>- A nucleus is composed of two types of particles, positively charged protons and neutral neutrons, except the nucleus of hydrogen, formed of one proton only.</4>
		</Section>
		<Section>
   			<0>IV. Quantity of electric charge</0>
			<1>The electron carries a negative charge: q(sub)e(/sub) = -1.6x10(sup)-19(/sup) C, while the proton carries a positive charge: q(sub)p(/sub) = 1.6x10(sup)-19(/sup) C. The neutron does not have an electric charge: it is neutral.</1>
			<2>In general, matter is neutral, i.e., it contains equal number of positive and negative charges, otherwise it will be ionized.</2>
			<3>On the macroscopic scale, the "electric charge", carried by a body, is due to a lack or excess of electrons. If an object has an excess or lack of N electrons, its charge will be, in absolute value: |q| = Nxe = Nx1.6x10(sup)-19(/sup) C.</3>
		</Section>
		<Section>
   			<0>V. Insulators and conductors</0>
			<1>In solids, the moving charges are the free electrons.</1>
			<2>A material is called perfect conductor if, when charged, the charge carriers are able to move freely in the material.</2>
			<3>An insulator (or dielectric) is perfect, if the charge carriers are not able to move freely in the material but localized in the same place where they were produced.</3>
			<4>Each material is located in some place between these two extreme states. (br)Thus every charge created on a material, is distributed over the surface, in a case of a conductor, or remains in place where it was produced, in the case of an insulator.</4>
			<5>&lt;B&gt;Example :&lt;/B&gt;</5>
			<6>Let's do an experiment of static electricity: rub a metallic rod with a rag. It won't attract bits of paper, the rod is not charged.</6>
			<7>&lt;B&gt;Why? &lt;/B&gt;</7>
			<8>Since we are ourselves good conductors, the electric charges that are pulled out of the rag, and transferred to the rod, are then transferred to our bodies. Hence, there will be no particular electric effect on the rod.</8>
			<9>For the success of this experiment, the charged object should be isolated, by holding it with an insulating material for example.</9>
		</Section>
		<Section>
   			<0>VI. Electrifying an object by rubbing </0>
			<1>By rubbing a glass rod with a silk, electrons are pulled out of the glass which becomes positively charged. The pulled electrons stick on the silk which becomes negatively charged.</1>
			<2>By rubbing an ebonite rod with a fur, electrons are pulled out of the fur which becomes positively charged. The pulled electrons stick on the ebonite rod which becomes negatively charged.</2>
			<3>In the same way, we can charge a plastic ruler by rubbing it with a piece of cloth. This phenomenon also includes the cloth.</3>
		</Section>
		<Section>
   			<0>VII. Electrification by induction</0>
			<1>We approach a negatively charged rod to a metallic sphere that is electrically neutral.</1>
			<2>The free electrons of the rod repel electrons to the opposite face of the ball. As a result, the portion of the ball in front of the rod becomes positively charged and the other side becomes negatively charged.</2>
			<3>If we approach a positively charged rod to an electrically neutral metallic ball.</3>
			<4>The positive charges of the rod attract electrons of the ball to their side. As a result, the portion of the ball in front of the rod becomes negatively charged and the other side becomes positively charged.</4>
			<5>&lt;B&gt;Electroscope:&lt;/B&gt;</5>
			<6>An electroscope is a simple device used to detect the presence of an electric charge by mutual repulsion of aluminum papers or any metal papers.</6>
			<7>We approach a charged object close to an electroscope.</7>
			<8>If the object is negatively charged, it will repel free electrons of the electroscope. There will be a large number of these electrons in the papers that become both negatively charged and repel each other.</8>
			<9>If the object is positively charged, it will attract free electrons of the electroscope to its side. Due to the lack of electrons in the papers, they become both positively charged and repel each other.</9>
			<10>This dis-symmetry in the distribution of electrons under the effect of the electric charges, is called electrification by induction.</10>
			<11>The electroscope remains neutral, for it does not exchange electric charges with other object.</11>
		</Section>
		<Section>
   			<0>VIII. Electrification by contact</0>
			<1>When a body A, which is negatively charged, touches a neutral body B, some electrons move to the body B which becomes negatively charged.</1>
			<2>When a positively charged body A, touches a neutral body B, it attracts some electrons of the body B. B becomes positively charged all like A.</2>
			<3>If the body B is an insulator, the charges formed on it cannot move, they remain localized. But if B is a conductor, the formed charges are able to move, thus they spread quickly over the surface of B.</3>
		</Section>
		<Section>
   			<0>IX. The Law of conservation of charge</0>
			<1>If many objects share electric charge between each other, the sum of all their charges remains constant. This is the law of conservation of charges.</1>
		</Section>
		<Section>
   			<0>X. Coulomb's Law</0>
			<1>The french physicist, Charles Augustin de Coulomb (1736-1806), was the first to state the following law:</1>
			<2>Two point charges A and B, separated by a distance d, and carrying the charges q(sub)A(/sub) and q(sub)B(/sub), exert on each other attractive forces (if q(sub)A(/sub) and q(sub)B(/sub) are of opposite signs), or repulsive forces (if q(sub)A(/sub) and q(sub)B(/sub) are of the same sign). These forces belong to the straight line joining the two objects. They have the same value:</2>
			<3>in a vacuum or in air, the constant k = 9. 10(sup)9(/sup) S.I.</3>
			<4>Charge of object A in C</4>
			<5>Charge of object B in C</5>
			<6>Distance between A and B in m</6>
			<7>attractive or repulsive force in N</7>
			<8>&lt;B&gt;Example 1:&lt;/B&gt;</8> 
			<9>Repulsive forces occur, because q(sub)A(/sub) and q(sub)B(/sub) are of the same sign.</9>
			<10>&lt;B&gt;Example 2:&lt;/B&gt;</10>
			<11>Attractive forces occur, for q(sub)A(/sub) and q(sub)B(/sub) are of opposite signs.</11>
		</Section>

	</English>

	<French>
		<Parameters>
			<Title>&lt;B&gt;Electrostatique&lt;B/&gt;</Title>
			<Number>1</Number>
			<Play>Lancer</Play>
			<Pause>Pause</Pause>
			<Previous>Précédent</Previous>
			<Next>Suivant</Next>
			<Replay>Relancer</Replay>
			<Restart>Retour</Restart>
			<Section>Section </Section>
			<End>&lt;B&gt;Tu as terminé ce chapitre. &lt;B/&gt;</End>
			<End1>Utilise le menu déroulant en haut de page pour revenir à une section particulière.</End1>
			<Copyright>Copyright 2010 - Tous droits réservés</Copyright>
			<CopyrightEnd>Contenu et animations par EduLab</CopyrightEnd>
			<Sens>Sens de propagation</Sens>
			<Chap>&lt;B&gt;Chap&lt;B/&gt;</Chap>
		</Parameters>
		<Section>
   			<0>I. Introduction</0>
			<1>Si on frotte un crayon en plastique sur un morceau de jeans, et si on rapproche ce crayon d'un bout de papier, on constate que le crayon attire le papier.</1>
			<2>Ce type de phénomène est même rapporté par Thalès de Milet, aux alentours de 600 av. J.-C. : il avait observé l'attraction de brindilles de paille par l'ambre jaune frotté. Le mot "électricité", qui désigne l'ensemble de ces manifestations, provient de "elektron", qui signifie ambre en grec.</2>
			<3>Pour interpréter ce phénomène et bien d'autres phénomènes naturels, les savants ont attribué à la matière une propriété, l'électrisation, qui est la cause des forces électriques, en introduisant le concept de charge électrique.</3>
		</Section>		
		<Section>
   			<0>II. Interaction électrostatique</0>
			<1>Expérimentalement, on constate l'existence de deux espèces d'électricité, pour cela on introduit la notion de charge positive et de charge négative.</1>
			<2>- Deux corps se repoussent s'ils portent une charge de même signe.</2>
			<3>- Deux corps s'attirent s'ils portent des charges de signe opposé.</3>
			<4>Dans le système d'unités international, l'unité de la quantité de charge électrique est le Coulomb (symbole C).</4>
		</Section>
		<Section>
   			<0>III. Aspect électrique de la matière</0>
			<1>Des savants ont élaboré un modèle de la structure de la matière. Selon ce modèle:</1>
			<2>- Toute matière est constituée d'atomes de forme et de dimension différentes.</2>
			<3>- Chaque atome est constitué d'un noyau chargé positivement autour duquel se trouve des électrons chargés négativement, qui sont en mouvement.</3>
			<4>- Un noyau est constitué de deux genres de particule, les protons chargés positivement et les neutrons qui n'ont pas de charge.</4>
		</Section>
		<Section>
   			<0>IV. Quantité de charges</0>
			<1>L'électron possède une charge négative q(sub)e(/sub) = -1,6.10(sup)-19(/sup) C et le proton une charge positive q(sub)p(/sub) = 1,6.10(sup)-19(/sup) C. Ces charges ont des valeurs absolues égales à e =1,6.10(sup)-19(/sup) C. Le neutron ne possède pas de charge électrique: il est neutre.</1>
			<2>En général, la matière est neutre, c'est-à-dire, elle contient autant de charge positive que de charge négative, sinon elle est ionisée.</2>
			<3>A l'échelle macroscopique, la "charge électrique" portée par un corps correspond à un défaut ou un excès d'électrons. Si un objet possède un excès ou un défaut de N électrons, sa charge est, en valeur absolue: |q| = N.e = N.1,6 .10(sup)-19(/sup) C.</3>
		</Section>
		<Section>
   			<0>V. Isolants et conducteurs</0>
			<1>Dans les corps solides, les charges mobiles sont les électrons libres.</1>
			<2>Un matériau est dit conducteur parfait si, lorsqu'il devient électrisé, il laisse les porteurs de charge non compensés se déplacer librement dans lui.</2>
			<3>Ce sera un isolant (ou diélectrique) parfait si les porteurs de charge non compensés ne peuvent pas se déplacer librement mais restent localisés à l'endroit où ils ont été déposés.</3>
			<4>Un matériau quelconque se situe évidemment quelque part entre ces deux états extrêmes.(br)Donc toute charge créée sur un matériau se répartit sur la surface, dans le cas d'un conducteur, ou reste localisée là où elle a été créée, pour un isolant.</4>
			<5>&lt;B&gt;Exemple:&lt;/B&gt;</5>
			<6>Refaisons une expérience d'électricité statique: prenons une tige métallique par la main et frottons-la avec un chiffon. La tige ne sera pas électrisée.</6>
			<7>&lt;B&gt;Pourquoi?&lt;/B&gt;</7>
			<8>Etant nous-mêmes d'assez bons conducteurs, les charges électriques arrachées au chiffon et transférées à la tige sont ensuite transférées sur nous et l'on ne verra pas d'effet électrique particulier au niveau de la tige.</8>
			<9>Pour que cette expérience réussisse (ainsi que les autres proposées), il est nécessaire d'isoler électriquement l'objet conducteur électrisé en le tenant avec un matériau isolant.</9>
		</Section>
		<Section>
   			<0>VI. Électrisation d'un objet par frottement</0>
			<1>Lorsqu'on frotte un bâton de verre avec un chiffon, on arrache des électrons au verre, ce qui le rend positif. Les électrons se déposent sur le chiffon qui devient négatif.</1>
			<2>Lorsqu'on frotte un bâton d'ébonite avec un chiffon, on arrache des électrons au chiffon ce qui le rend positif. Ces électrons se déposent sur le bâton d'ébonite qui devient négatif. </2>
			<3>On peut ainsi charger une feuille de plastique en la frottant. C'est aussi ce phénomène qui provoque l'électrisation des vêtements.</3>
		</Section>
		<Section>
   			<0>VII. Electrisation par influence (induction)</0>
			<1>On approche une tige chargée négativement d'une boule métallique électriquement nulle.</1>
			<2>Les électrons libres de la tige repoussent les électrons en face de la boule. Par suite, la partie de la boule en face de la tige devient chargée positivement, et l'autre partie devient chargée négativement.</2>
			<3>On approche une tige chargée positivement d'une boule métallique électriquement nulle.</3>
			<4>Les charges positives de la tige attirent les électrons de la boule. Par suite, la partie de la boule en face de la tige devient chargée négativement, et l'autre partie devient chargée positivement.</4>
			<5>&lt;B&gt;Electroscope:&lt;/B&gt;</5>
			<6>Un électroscope est un simple appareil qui détecte la présence d'une charge électrique par la répulsion mutuelle de feuilles d'aluminium.</6>
			<7>On approche un objet électrisé de l'électroscope.</7>
			<8>Si le corps est chargé négativement, il repousse les électrons libres de l'électroscope. Ces électrons se retrouvent en excès dans les feuilles qui deviennent négatives et se repoussent.</8>
			<9>Si le corps est chargé positivement, il attire les électrons libres de l'électroscope. Ces électrons se retrouvent en défaut dans les feuilles qui deviennent positives et se repoussent.</9>
			<10>Cette dissymétrie de répartition des électrons sous l'influence des charges électriques s'appelle électrisation par influence ou par induction.</10>
			<11>L'électroscope reste globalement neutre car il n'y a pas d'échange d'électricité avec un autre corps. Lorsqu'on retire le corps chargé, les électrons reviennent à leurs positions initiales et les feuilles de l'électroscope redescendent.</11>
		</Section>
		<Section>
   			<0>VIII. Electrisation par contact</0>
			<1>Lorsqu'un corps A chargé négativement touche un corps neutre B, des électrons passent sur le corps neutre B qui devient lui aussi négatif.</1>
			<2>Lorsqu'un corps A chargé positivement touche un corps neutre B, il attire des électrons du corps neutre B qui devient alors positif.</2>
			<3>Si le corps B est isolant, les charges y déposées ne peuvent pas se déplacer. Si B est conducteur, les charges déposées peuvent se déplacer, elles se répartissent rapidement à sa surface.</3>
		</Section>
		<Section>
   			<0>IX. Loi de conservation des charges électriques</0>
			<1>Si plusieurs corps échangent de l'électricité entre eux seulement, la somme des charges de ces corps reste la même. C'est la loi de conservation des charges électriques.</1>
		</Section>
		<Section>
   			<0>X. La loi de Coulomb</0>
			<1>C'est le physicien français Charles Augustin de Coulomb (1736-1806) qui énonça le premier la loi suivante:</1>
			<2>Deux objets ponctuels A et B, séparés par une distance d et portant des charges q(sub)A(/sub) et q(sub)B(/sub), exercent l'un sur l'autre des forces attractives (si q(sub)A(/sub) et q(sub)B(/sub) sont de signe contraire) ou répulsives (si q(sub)A(/sub) et q(sub)B(/sub) sont de même signe), dirigées suivant la droite qui les joint. Ces forces ont la même valeur:</2>
			<3>Constante avec k = 9. 10(sup)9(/sup) S.I. dans le vide ou dans l'air.</3>
			<4>Charge du corps A en C</4>
			<5>Charge du corps B en C</5>
			<6>Distance entre A et B en m</6>
			<7>Force d'attraction ou de répulsion en N</7>
			<8>&lt;B&gt;Exemple 1:&lt;/B&gt;</8> 
			<9>Forces répulsives car q(sub)A(/sub) et q(sub)B(/sub) sont de même signe.</9>
			<10>&lt;B&gt;Exemple 2:&lt;/B&gt;</10>
			<11>Forces attractives car q(sub)A(/sub) et q(sub)B(/sub) sont de signes contraires.</11>
		</Section>

	</French>
</root>
